Processed food companies
spend a lot of effort
trying to make their products seem
healthier than they actually are.
Does vitamin and mineral fortification
make dayglow marshmallows healthy?
Watch to find out.
"Are Fortified Kids' Breakfast Cereals
Healthy or Just Candy?"
In 1941, the American Medical
Association's Council
on Foods and Nutrition was presented
with a new product, Vi-Chocolin,
a vitamin fortified chocolate bar,
offered ostensibly as a product
of high nutritive value, but in reality,
intended for promotion to the public
as a kind of vitaminized candy.
Surely something like that
couldn't happen today,
but that's the entire sugary cereal
industry's business model.
Twelve vitamins and minerals.
Way better than those marshmallow
Froot Loops with just a measly 11.
Nutrients are added to breakfast
cereals as a marketing gimmick
to create an aura of healthfulness.
If those same nutrients
were added to soda,
would we feed our kids
Coke for breakfast?
We might as well spray cotton
candy with vitamins too.
As one medical journal
editorial read,
Adding vitamins and minerals to
sugary cereals is worse than useless.
The subtle message is that
somehow it's safe to eat more.
General Mills' "Grow up strong with
Big G kids" cereals' ad campaign
featured products like Lucky
Charms, Trix, and Cocoa Puffs.
That's like the dairy industry promoting
ice cream to get your calcium.
Kids who eat presweetened
breakfast cereals may get
more than 20% of their daily
calories from added sugar.
Most sugar in the American diet
comes from beverages like soda,
but breakfast cereals represent the third
largest food source of added sugars
in the diets of children and adolescents,
wedged between candy and ice cream.
On a per serving basis,
there is more added sugar
in a cereal like Frosted Flakes than
there is in frosted chocolate cake,
brownies, or a frosted doughnut.
Kellogg and General Mills argue that
breakfast cereals only contribute
a relatively small amount of
sugar to the diets of children,
less than soda, for example.
This is a perfect example of
a psychological phenomenon
known as diffusion of responsibility.
That's like every restaurant in the
country arguing that their individual
contribution to the problem of
second-hand smoke is relatively
tiny, therefore should be exempted
from the smoking ban.
Each and every source of added
sugar should be reduced.
The industry argues that most
of their cereals have less
than 10 grams of sugar per serving,
but when Consumer Reports measured
how much youngsters actually poured,
they were found to serve
themselves about 50% more
than the suggested serving size
for most of the tested cereals.
The average portion of Frosted
Flakes they poured for themselves
contained 18 grams of sugar—4.5
teaspoons, or 6 sugar packets worth.
It's been estimated that a child
eating one serving a day
of the average children's
cereal would consume
close to 10 pounds of sugar in a year,
nearly 1,000 spoonfuls of sugar.
General Mills offers the "Mary Poppins
defense," arguing that it's those
spoonfuls of sugar that help the
medicine go down, explaining that
if sugar is removed from bran cereal, it
would have the consistency of sawdust.
If we couldn't add sugar, our
cereals would be unpalatable.
If one has to add sugar to a product to
make it edible, that should be a sign.
That's a characteristic of so-called
ultra-processed foods,
where you have to pack them full
of things like sugar, salt, flavorings
since they have had their natural
intrinsic flavors processed out,
and you have to kind of mask any
unpleasantries in the final product.
The president of the
Cereal Institute has argued
that without sugary cereals, kids
might not eat breakfast at all,
similar to dairy industry arguments
that removing chocolate milk
from school cafeterias would
risk kids skipping lunch.
He also stressed we must
consider the alternatives.
As Kellogg's director
of nutrition once put it:
I would suggest that
Fruit Loops as a snack
are much better than potato
chips or a sweet roll.
You know there's a problem when
the only way to make your product
look good is to compare it
to Pringles and Cinnabon.